Guide to the Jay C. Waldman Papers, 1968-2003 AIS.2007.10
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Office of the Governor, 1979-1986; X.
  Newly elected Governor Thornburgh immediately began forming his all-important staff. First on the list was the appointment of Jay C. Waldman as Executive Assistant to the Governor. Waldman and Thornburgh had by then a mutual well-established respect and admiration for one another. Waldman had not only been with Thornburgh in various positions since 1970, but also had master minded the campaign for Governor with all the meticulous attention to the needs and problems in Pennsylvania. Thus Waldman was considered early as the key strategist and tactician to accomplish the administration's goals. It was Waldman who would, as Thornburgh states in his autobiography "conduct a political assessment, determining whether the policy was consistent with our overall philosophy and campaign themes, how key supporters or interest groups were likely to react (and whether that mattered) and how the policy fit into the long-term big picture." Waldman had expanded legal responsibilities after his appointment by Thornburgh in January 1981 to the newly created position of General Counsel (OGC) to the Governor. In that role Waldman not only assured the Governor and others in the executive branch of legal counsel to protect their interests, but also served to bring an independent perspective in reviewing the numerous cases that involved the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania. There is one video of Reagan campaign ads done by Thornburgh housed separately in media storage. This series is further divided into five subseries: Waldman Governor's Office Files, Governor's Office Legal, Dick Thornburgh Files, Thornburgh Administration, and Political.
  - Waldman Governor's Office Files, 1963-1985; 1.
    These files are both when Waldman (JCW) served as Executive Assistant to the Governor in 1981 and following as General Counsel. This subseries represents his specific leadership, including overall accomplishments as compared with legal cases and political matters that follow in subsequent subseries. They were better identified with Waldman's own labeling. Of particular value are folders relating to the organization of the Governor's Office in the early administration, two major folders of accomplishments, and the Waldman correspondence. The correspondence files contain occasional memoranda and drafts of letters. The Waldman's Governor's Office Files date from 1963 to 1985.
    - Memo, Cabinet meetings, February–April 1979 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Memo, Organization & Operation of Governor's Office, June 1, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Memo, Executive Services Detail, September 21, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - JCW and Roberta Waldman Employment Certificates, March 1980 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - First year department updates, Aging, undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - First year department updates, Agriculture, December 3, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - First year department updates, Banking, October 1, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - First year department updates, Community Affairs, August 1979 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - First year department updates, Environmental Resources, undated (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - First year department updates, General Services, October 9, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - First year department updates, Insurance, March 4, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - First year department updates, Military Affairs, January-October 1979 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - First year department updates, PennDOT, October, November 1979 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - First year department updates, PA State Police, October 11, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - First year department updates, State, December 14, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - OGC, Staff/salaries, 1980-1984 (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - OGC, Bond counsel, 1975-1983 (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - OGC, Budget information, 1979-1984 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - OGC, DOH registrars' case (McMullen v Thornburgh), 1979-1983 (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - OGC, Contract/Regulations, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - OGC, Pittsburgh Convention Center, 1982-1985 (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - OGC, Law, undated (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - OGC, Department activities, 1981-1983 (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - OGC, Department activities, 1981-1983 (Box 17, Folder 24)
    - OGC, Executive mansion, 1982 (Box 17, Folder 25)
    - OGC, AT&T, 1982 (Box 17, Folder 26)
    - OGC, Transfer agent monies, 1963-1981 (Box 17, Folder 27)
    - OGC, General obligation bonds, 1970-1983 (Box 17, Folder 28)
    - OGC, PA Housing Finance Agency, 1981-1982 (Box 17, Folder 29)
    - OGC, PA Industrial Development Authority, 1970-1983 (Box 17, Folder 30)
    - OGC, Public School Building Authority, September 13, 1982 (Box 17, Folder 31)
    - OGC, Cohen opposition, February 2, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 32)
    - OGC, Second Annual Report, Part I, 1984 achievements, March 4, 1985 (Box 17, Folder 33)
    - OGC, Second Annual Report, Part II, '84 accomplishments, January 3, 1985 (Box 17, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence from JCW, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 35)
    - Correspondence to/ from JCW, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence from JCW, 1981 (Box 17, Folder 37)
    - Correspondence from JCW, 1982 (Box 17, Folder 38)
    - Correspondence from JCW, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence from JCW, 1984 (Box 17, Folder 40)
    - Correspondence to/from JCW, 1985 (Box 17, Folder 41)
    - Personal, correspondence to, 1978-1985 (Box 17, Folder 42)
    - Personal, Roberta Waldman, 1979-1985 (Box 17, Folder 43)
    - Personal, Quotes, undated (Box 17, Folder 44)
    - Personal, JCW news clippings, 1979-1986 (Box 17, Folder 45)
    - Personal, Thornburgh's letter appointing JCW General Counsel, January 21, 1981 (Box 17, Folder 46)
    - New Release announcing JCW leaving administration, April 3, 1985 (Box 17, Folder 47)
  - Governor's Office Legal, 1980-1986; 2.
    The files are grouped in Waldman's original order and with his identifying labels. Waldman's notes and many actual cases in multiple formats and accompanying court documentation are also included. Some are more "political" in nature, while others are more issue related. At the end of this subseries there are extensive files about a case to U.S. Court of Appeals, and a subsequent Supreme Court case argued on behalf of Commonwealth of Pennsylvania by Waldman and others. Case name: Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, et al, Petitioners, v. Delaware Valley Citizens' Council for Clean Air, et al, Respondents. It is abbreviated in folder titles: PA v Del. These materials date from 1980 to 1986.
    - O'Pake / Fumo, 1980, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Cigna, 1983-1986 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - State Health Facility, 1984-1985 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Mid-Atlantic Legal Foundation, 1983-1985 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - H. Craig Lewis, Legal Fees, 1981-1984 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Camiel v. Thornburgh & Larson, 1984 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Camiel v. Thornburgh, 1984-1985 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Office General Counsel / Office Attorney General, 1981-1986 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Turnpike Commission, 1984-1985 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Hixon v. Bartle, 1980-1983 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Hixon v. Bartle, 1980-1983 (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Hixon v. Bartle, 1980-1983 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Price v. Cohen, 1983 (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Price v. Cohen, 1983 (Box 18, Folder 14)
    - PSEA v. Thornburgh and Critchlow, 1982 (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - PSEA v. Thornburgh and Critchlow, 1982 (Box 18, Folder 16)
    - Zemprelli v. Cohen, 1983 (Box 18, Folder 17)
    - Governor v. McMullan, October 1981 (Box 18, Folder 18)
    - Supreme Court "Patronage" opinion, March 1980 (Box 18, Folder 19)
    - CAT Fund counsel expenses and billings, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 20)
    - 1984 salaried counsel fees report, April 3, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 21)
    - Senate Appropriations Committee, 1984 counsel report, April 3, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 22)
    - 1985 outside counsel fees report, January 24, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 23)
    - Report, 1985 outside counsel to Delaware River Port Authority, January 2, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 24)
    - Report, Oct – Dec 1985 outside counsel for DRPA and PATCO, February 19, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 25)
    - PAvDel, Legal Services Funding, undated (Box 18, Folder 26)
    - PAvDel, JCW notes, undated, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 27)
    - PAvDel, Historical survey attorney's fee awards, 1981 (Box 18, Folder 28)
    - PAvDel, Case news clippings, March 1986 (Box 18, Folder 29)
    - PA v Del, Brief drafts of Petitioners, to US Court of Appeals, 1985 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - PA v Del, Petitioners Petition to US Court of Appeals, 1985 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - PA v Del, Petitioners Brief to Supreme Court, 1985-1986 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - PA v Del, Amicus Curiae Petitioners, 1985-1986 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - PA v Del, Petitioners reply and supplemental briefs, 1985-1986 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - PA v Del, Respondents brief and supplemental appendix, 1985-1986 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - PA v Del, Respondents Amicus Curiae, 1985-1986 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - PA v Del, USA Brief, 1985-1986 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - PA v Del, Guide for counsel presenting to Supreme Court, June 1985 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - PA v Del, Official Supreme Court transcript, March 3, 1986 (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - PA v Del, Supreme Court case syllabus, decided, July 2, 1986 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - PA v Del, Respondent Amicus Curiae, September 1986 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Dick Thornburgh Files, 1979-1986; 3.
    These files specifically relate to Thornburgh and associated political matters that Waldman, as the Governor's closest advisor and counselor, kept very careful track of. There are also some Governor's speeches and testimony, press kit, and PA informational booklets and publications. The files in this subseries date from 1979 to 1986.
    - Executive orders of Shapp and Thornburgh (incomplete), 1971-1983 (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - Governor messages (Selected), 1981-1986 (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - Testimony, 1979 (Box 19, Folder 15)
    - Political RLT, including September 1985 poll, 1982-1985 (Box 19, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, 1979-1986 (Box 19, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, MacLeod final report, October 1979 (Box 19, Folder 18)
    - Governor mailings, 1979-1985 (Box 19, Folder 19)
    - Speeches, 1979 (Box 19, Folder 20)
    - Speeches, 1980 (Box 19, Folder 21)
    - Speeches, 1982 (Box 19, Folder 22)
    - Speeches, 1983 (Box 19, Folder 23)
    - Speeches, 1984 (Box 19, Folder 24)
    - Speeches, 1985 (Box 19, Folder 25)
    - Speeches, 1986 (Box 19, Folder 26)
    - China – Japan Trade Mission, 1980 (Box 19, Folder 27)
    - HB 962, Elected Attorney General, bill signing certificate, October 15, 1980 (Box 19, Folder 28)
    - Press Kit, You've Got a Friend In PA, March 25, 1980 (Box 19, Folder 29)
    - Press Kit, Policy and Budget updates, March 1980 (Box 19, Folder 30)
    - Pennsylvania Booklet, Business Has a Friend in PA, 1984 (Box 19, Folder 31)
  - Thornburgh Administration, 1973-1986; 4.
    Thornburgh Administration files relate to issues including Three Mile Island (TMI), achievements of the administration, extensive monitoring of issues and achievements by Marketing Opinion Research (MOR), and news clippings about issues and the administration. Again, these files relate to other similar material in the Dick Thornburgh Papers. These materials date 1973 to 1986.
    - Issue, Graterford, Bureau of Correction, 1983 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Issue, Graterford, Civil rights, 1983-1984 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Issue, Graterford, correspondence, 1983 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Issue, Graterford, U.S.A. v. Hawaii, 1983 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Issue, Graterford, CRIPA, 1983 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Issue, Graterford, JCW notes, 1983 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Issue, Graterford, news clips, November 1983 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Issue, Abortion, Roe v. Wade, December 1973 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Issue, Abortion, Pro-Life Package, July 1981 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Issue, Abortion, Senate Bill 742, December 1981 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Issue, Abortion, Senate Bill 439, June 1982 (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Issue, Budget, General Fund Summary, 1979-1982 (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - Issue, Budget, Moody's Presentation by PA, September 13, 1984 (Box 20, Folder 13)
    - Issue, Budget, Legislative Budget & Finance Report, January 1986 (Box 20, Folder 14)
    - Issue, Collective Bargaining by Commonwealth Attorneys, 1981 (Box 20, Folder 15)
    - Issue, Crime Commission, Report, 1984 (Box 20, Folder 16)
    - Issue, Ethics Commission, 1981 (Box 20, Folder 17)
    - Issue, Ethics Commission, Dechert firm appointment, 1981 (Box 20, Folder 18)
    - Issue, Ethics Commission, 1982 (Box 20, Folder 19)
    - Issue, Ethics Commission, 1983 (Box 20, Folder 20)
    - Issue, Economic Development, 1983-1986 (Box 20, Folder 21)
    - Issue, Liquor Control Board (LCB), October 1979 (Box 20, Folder 22)
    - Issue, Merit Selection of Judges, 1983-1984 (Box 20, Folder 23)
    - Issue, Merit Selection of Judges, 1980-1984 (Box 20, Folder 24)
    - Issue, Merit Selection of Judges Report, September 1983 (Box 20, Folder 25)
    - Issue, PA Abstract, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 26)
    - Issue, Philadelphia Convention Center, 1985-1986 (Box 20, Folder 27)
    - Issue, Saturn, February 19, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 28)
    - Issue, Saturn Presentation, Vol. I, February 1985 (Box 20, Folder 29)
    - Issue, Saturn Presentation, Vol. II, February 1985 (Box 20, Folder 30)
    - Issue, Saturn Presentation, Vol. III, February 1985 (Box 20, Folder 31)
    - Issue, TMI, March 28–April 1, 1979 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Issue, TMI, April 2-April 4, 1979 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Issue TMI, April 2-April 3, 1979 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Issue, TMI, April 4-April 6, 1979 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Issue, TMI, April 5-April 7, 1979 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Issue, TMI, April 9-April 12, 1979 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Issue, TMI, April 13-April 20, 1979 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Issue, TMI, April 23-April 30, 1979 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Issue, TMI, May 1979 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Issue, TMI, NRC Licensing Met Ed, April 1977 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Issue, TMI, Unused Emergency Proclamation, April 1979 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Issue, TMI, undated, April 1979 (Box 21, Folder 12)
    - Issue, TMI, Department of Health, April 1979-April 1980 (Box 21, Folder 13)
    - Issue, TMI, Cleanup Plan, July 1981 (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - Achievements, January 14, 1981 (Box 21, Folder 15)
    - Achievements Books Content Lists, April 28, 1981 (Box 21, Folder 16)
    - Achievements Vol I (Aging-Economic Development) (Box 21, Folder 17)
    - Achievements Vol I (Education-Environment) (Box 21, Folder 18)
    - Achievements Vol I (Exec Management-Fiscal Affairs/Taxation) (Box 21, Folder 19)
    - Achievements Vol II (Health-Local Government) (Box 21, Folder 20)
    - Achievements Vol II (MH/MR-Regulation) (Box 21, Folder 21)
    - Achievements Vol II (Transportation-Misc) (Box 21, Folder 22)
    - Achievements Vol III (SW PA) (Box 21, Folder 23)
    - Achievements Vol III (NE PA) (Box 21, Folder 24)
    - Achievements Vol III (Erie, PA) (Box 21, Folder 25)
    - Achievements Vol III (Adams-Cumberland) (Box 21, Folder 26)
    - Achievements Vol III (Dauphin-Mercer) (Box 21, Folder 27)
    - Achievements Vol III (Monroe-York) (Box 21, Folder 28)
    - Achievements Updated Contents List, August, 1982) (Box 21, Folder 29)
    - Achievements updated (Integrity in Government - Transportation) (Box 21, Folder 30)
    - Achievements updated (Crime-Women) (Box 21, Folder 31)
    - Achievements updated (Blacks-Local Gov) (Box 21, Folder 32)
  - Political, 1979-1986; 5.
    Waldman, as part of his role as advisor to Governor Thornburgh, carefully monitored and kept track of Pennsylvania politics, national GOP and other campaigns, and electoral matters. This would be common for advisors to persons holding elected positions. There is considerable information from market opinion research (MOR) prepared for the Governor Thornburgh Committee (GTC) and other from consulting organization: "Decision Making Information." Additionally, there are political news clippings about Thornburgh and other political figures as well as some miscellaneous political articles, correspondence, and election results. This material dates from 1979 to 1986.
    - MOR Philadelphia Summary Tables, April 1979 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - MOR Philadelphia Marston Mayoral, August 1979 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - MOR Statewide Data for GOP, October 1979 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - MOR Statewide Analysis for GOP, October 1979 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - MOR Statewide Data for GOP, July 1980 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - MOR Pennsylvania Tables, July 1980 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - MOR Statewide Analysis for GTC, July 1981 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - MOR Statewide Data for GTC, July 1981 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - MOR Miscellaneous Data for GTC, July 1981 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - MOR Statewide Summary Tables for GTC, September 1982 (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - MOR Statewide Analysis for GTC, December 1983 (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - MOR Statewide Data for GTC, December 1983 (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - MOR Statewide Data for GTC, December 1983 (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - MOR Statewide Data for GTC, January 1984 (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - MOR Selected Statewide Data for GTC, May 1984 (Box 22, Folder 15)
    - MOR Selected New York Tables, February 1985 (Box 22, Folder 16)
    - Thornburgh news clips, 1979-1980 (Box 22, Folder 17)
    - Thornburgh news clips, 1981-1982 (Box 22, Folder 18)
    - Thornburgh news clips, 1983-1984 (Box 22, Folder 19)
    - Thornburgh news clips, 1985-1986 (Box 22, Folder 20)
    - News clippings: staff (Box 22, Folder 21)
    - Political booklets, maps, undated (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, news clips, 1979-1986 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous, Scranton-Casey campaign, 1985-1986 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Memo, Judicial Nominations, 1980 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Waldman Op-Ed Column re LCB, June 1981 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Draft, Appellate Court Campaign, 1981 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - President Reagan Accomplishments, January 1984 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Reagan-Bush Campaign, 1980 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Memo, PA Voter Registration, 1980 (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - GOP National Committee and RGA, 1978-1986 (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - PA Republican State Committee, 1980 (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - PA Republican State Committee, 1968-1978 (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - Lists, 1984-1986 (Box 23, Folder 13)
    - Lists, 1979-1983 (Box 23, Folder 14)
    - PA Election Returns, 1979-1986 (Box 23, Folder 15)
    - GTC, 1979 (Box 23, Folder 16)
    - GTC, 1980 (Box 23, Folder 17)
    - GTC, 1981 (Box 23, Folder 18)
    - GTC, 1982 (Box 23, Folder 19)
    - GTC, 1983 (Box 23, Folder 20)
    - GTC, 1984 (Box 23, Folder 21)
    - GTC, 1985 (Box 23, Folder 22)
    - GTC donor lists, 1981, 1984 (Box 23, Folder 23)
    - GTC donor lists, undated (Box 23, Folder 24)
    - Heinz campaign, 1982 (Box 23, Folder 25)
    - Volume, 32nd Republican National Convention, Detroit, 1980 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Volume, Decision Making Information, PA Tabulations for GTC, October 1, 1985 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Volume, Decision Making Information, PA Statewide Republicans, September 1986 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Decision Making Information, PA cross-tabulations for GTC, October 1985 (Box 24, Folder 4)